# Asim Zulfiqar

Munich, Germany | emmiasim67@gmail.com | +49 176 8495 4774 | | linkedin.com/in/asimzulfiqar

### **Profile**

I am a highly skilled and experienced Electronic engineer with a BS in Electronic Engineering and an MS in photonics, Integrated circuits, sensors, and networks. I have extensive knowledge and experience in IoT, embedded systems, python programming, and STEM training. I am a strong communicator and have been creating educational content on IoT, specifically MQTT and embedded systems, on YouTube and in my personal blog. Currently, I am working on an agriculture-based IoT project with LRZ.

# **Key Skills**

- Programming languages: Proficient in C, Python, and MATLAB.
- IoT: skilled in IoT Clouds (AWS, Azure, Cloud MQTT, TTN), data protocols (HTTPS, MQTT, Coap, Web-sockets), and network protocols (Wi-Fi, BLE, ZIGBEE, LORAWAN, NB-IoT, LTE).
- Development Boards: Arduino, Raspberry Pi, ESP, LoRa Modules, GPS, and NrF boards.
- Applications: Android studio, development using Flutter, Tkinter, PyQT.
- DevOps: CI/CD tools, Docker, Ansible, Grafana, Prometheus.
- Web APIs: REST API, Fast, XML/JSON/YAML.

# Experience

### Scientific programmer for IoT Research projects

Sep 2022 - Present

Leibniz Rechenzentrum (LRZ) - Garching bei München, Germany

- Participation in real time IoT data collection via LORA WAN, TTN, and MQTT.
- Definition and implementation of REST APIs for exchange of IoT sensor data.
- Design and implementation of a web-based user interface to InfluxDB using Grafana.
- Extension of automatic monitoring of data delivery and alerting with Prometheus.
- Virtual server management in the LRZ Compute Cloud using Ansible.

#### **Embedded and IoT developer**

Nov 2017 - Sep 2022

Fiverr and Upwork - Freelance (Remote)

- Completed over 300+ projects/orders with positive feedbacks on Fiverr and Upwork.
- Services included: embedded systems (Arduino, Raspberry Pi, ESP8266, ESP32, Nrf52), IoT development & clouds (MQTT, HTTP, AWS, IoT Azure, TTN), online STEM training, mobile application development, computer programming (Python, Java, C, C++), and technical content writing.
- Worked with companies and individuals all around the globe in different industries such as health, automobile, automation, agriculture, and more.
- Utilised my expertise to provide solutions for clients' needs and exceed their expectations.

#### **Online STEM & Coding Instructor**

Jan 2022 - Jun 2022

First Code Academy - Hong Kong (Remote)

- Taught block, Scratch, Python programming, and application development using MIT App Inventor.
- Developed and implemented lesson plans to engage students and Collaborated with other instructors to design and deliver STEM programs for children.

#### IoT software developer

Aug 2021 - Dec 2021

Consorzio Nazionale Interuniversitario per le Telecomunicazioni (CNIT) - Pisa, Italy

- Developed software for a Container Tracking Device (CTD) using ESP32, Quectel BG96, and sensors.
- Developed software for GW NB-IoT/BLE Mesh provisioning and sensor data transmission to ICON cloud via UDP/JSON.
- Created a data model for the CTD in cooperation with the client (CNIT).

Jan 2019 - Dec 2019

Techtree - Karachi, Pakistan

- As a STEM trainer, instructed school students in learning block, scratch programming, basic Electronic Engineering, and made them familiarised with trending technologies such as AI and IoT.
- As an IoT developer, designed and developed IoT based products such as Smart Air conditioner controlling device, which can be controlled using the internet.

# **Education and Qualifications**

## Master in Photonic Integrated circuits, Sensors, and Networks

Sept 2020 - Aug 2022

Erasmus Mundus Joint Master's Degree (PIXNET)

Overall Grade: Distinction

Thesis: Analysis of CFO estimation method in eigen value domain.

Universities:

• Osaka University, Osaka, Japan

Aug 2022

• Aston University, Birmingham, United Kingdom

Mar 2022

• Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa, Italy

Aug 2021

# **Bachelors in Electronic Engineering**

jan 2015 - Dec 2018

University: Sir Syed University of Engineering and Technology, Karachi, Pakistan

Grade: Excellent (3.57 CGPA) – 3rd position (bronze medallist) in the batch of 250 students.

Final year project: Physical robotic Assistant (Robotics, IoT, embedded systems)

# **Additional Experience & Awards**

- Reviewed "Raspberry Pi and MQTT Essentials," book and "Privacy and Ethics on the Internet of Things" course.
- Content Creation: 45+ educational videos, tutorials, and how-to blogs on embedded systems, IoT, and programming, on my Youtube channel and blog.
- Selected as an Erasmus mundus scholarship winner (1 of 20 worldwide), 2020.
- Received Tuition Fee Waiver scholarship for outstanding performance in undergraduate studies, 2015-2018.

#### **Publications**

# Hands-on ESP32 with Arduino IDE: Unleash the power of IoT with ESP32 and build exciting projects with this practical guide by Asim Zulfigar

Jan 2024

ISBN: 9781837638031

# Quantum Computer Metrics and HPC Center Environmental Sensor Data Analysis Towards Fidelity Prediction

Nov 2023

Hossam Ahmed, Xiaolong Deng, Helmut Heller, Carla Guillen, *Asim Zulfiqar*, Martin Ruefnacht, Amit Jamadagni, Matthew Tovey, Martin Schulz, Laura Schulz

DOI: 10.1109/OCE57702.2023.10200

## Language skills

English (IELTS: 7.0), German (A2)

## **Projects**

- IoT wearable social band (freelance) Fiverr Buffalo's Motor bike, Japan.
- Smart Parking system Barrier using IoT (freelance) Fiverr Your Parking Space, UK.
- Indoor Golf setup (freelance) Fiverr Stracka Line, USA.
- Burn-in system for logging data (freelance) Fiverr Test-Solution Service Inc., Philippines.
- Escape Room (freelance) Fiverr Heage, France.
- Cars weighing system for motor sports (freelance) Upwork– gp24, Romania.